[Music]
right hello and welcome everyone
it's april 27 2022 and we're in actin
lab live stream number 42.2
welcome to the actinflab we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on this slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow a good video
etiquette for live streams
check out activeinference.org to learn
more about what's happening in the lab
all right well
here we are in
42.2 we're in our third discussion
around the paper
robot navigation as hierarchical active
inference by the authors listed here
and
this is a discussion where we're going
to pick up on a few different threads
that were arising in the dot one
and have a lot of time to explore some
of the formalisms and the robotics
aspects of the project and take any
questions that people are bringing up
and just randomly posting in the live
chat
so we'll just start with introductions
and saying hello and then we'll jump to
where we were leaving for last time or
leaving for this time from last time and
then just see where we go
so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i'll pass to blue
i'm blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and i will pass it to tim
and hi i'm a researcher in games belgium
and one of the co-authors of the paper
so feel free to ask me anything
wow three three researchers
walk into a dot too
do you have that kind of joke over there
tim
like
okay we'll start with the evolves
okay we had a a few different notes down
so
anyone who wants to pick one of these
threads up or we can return to some of
the formalisms and questions about the
robotics but we're just going to pick up
a thread and start with whoever wants to
go first so we mentioned
difference
different detail and implementation and
just like fun stories or things that
happened in the implementation
the idea of different types of maps
and where does emergence
fit into this
one thing i could
i could elaborate on is
basically from the last stream i think
blue brought up
the idea of um
when you enter a hotel room
everything kind of looks familiar rather
you might have never entered that
particular hotel room right
and
the question was how could this arise
from from this kind of model
because
here it's still kind of very
tightly coupled to whatever you're
observing in that particular environment
and it doesn't really seem to scale to
some something else
which is uh which is correct
and so for
for this kind of uh understanding i
think you
you'll need to build a system that goes
even higher in hierarchy and and higher
in abstraction levels
and
i've been thinking about this kind of um
emergence slash kind of models that
could give this kind of
behavior
and i think at some point
you'll need to
have a model that is completely
reasoning in abstract
concepts rather than
um
observations that that you can observe
in your sensory
streams
so
i could imagine that you
um
that you're building a layer on top
of
this model so here you basically
go from
camera inputs to a
graph based representation of your
environment
i could imagine that you
repeat this for
many different kinds of environments
which results which yields you a number
of
graphs that map to that particular
environment
and that at that point you start kind of
looking for patterns
in this repertoire of graphs that you
that you visited in the past
and you you start
figuring out structure in these grouse
like
bedrooms all have like the beds and
maybe a closet whereas kitchens rather
have a fridge and a
sink
and that you kind of see
these kind of repeating
things in certain graphs and that at
this level you kind of
make
a model that
classifies kind of each
type of environment into such a category
which will then
inform you or kind of
give you a prior on what kind of graph
to expect in in in a hotel room for
example
um
so i realized that i'm talking in very
vague and abstract ideas here because
yeah you don't have it yet but yeah i
i think that's kind of
a way how to
how it could
be done and
i look very much forward to to actually
head into this research direction as
well
in particular uh so if we would think
about how would would i implement it
then i would start with
first applying the current system on a
bunch of environments that have like uh
like two different categories for
example
um
so uh
and then
kind of learn
a model on these crop structures
and
in particular these these current
evolutions and in graph rural nets might
might be a an interesting
route to take to see can you learn
representations of
graphs or part of the graphs
and and like build related codes that
that
generates similar style graphs basically
and then you can kind of
navigate to real environments
then learn a model that that builds
similar graphs and then use that model
to kind of imagine
potentially similar
looking environment
but still this will be so if we would
implement it purely on on this level i
imagine it will still be very much tied
to um
to the observation level like you could
generate potential camera
frames
that kind of look like it's it's like
creating a generic model on this um
the ls un bedrooms data set so you can
kind of generate novel kind of bedrooms
but it's still very much tied to
the pixel level whereas i think to go to
a more semantic and human level um
reasoning like we do then at some point
you'll have to start have
more understanding carving up the
observation space into different kind of
objects and have
um
these kind of representations which are
totally not in in the current model
and
yeah
you'll have you'll need to have some
understanding at that level before
before you can
have reasoning like okay i go to a hotel
room and i expect there to find the tv
and remote control for tv basically
but yeah
yes blue
thanks that's uh super interesting and
kind of a good um maybe tie-in to like i
was also thinking about
different kinds of maps
more than just over some kind of spatial
scenario and and the the one obvious
uh idea that comes to mind is like a
semantic map over language uh in natural
language processing and
using this kind of hotel room scenario
as a topic like in the topic of politics
you expect to find right wing left ring
conservative liberal like you expect to
find all of these words in the topic of
politics if you're trying to model a
topic
and i just wonder what other if either
of you guys have ever thought about
other kinds of spaces that can be mapped
over like this like physical space
semantic space where else can we build
maps where we can kind of implement this
type of navigation
yeah i mean that's
that's a very interesting uh question
and actually i think one of the core
hypotheses that that adam and i are
investigating is basically that
and anything that is related to
to our cognition is
it
basically stems from building a kind of
map and then navigating it um
and how this could um
be more concrete size for different
kinds of maps of course this is a huge
huge effort and you'll need to have like
um
experts on a certain domain in order to
kind of
think about is this possible and how
could it be
um
and for some topics it's pretty
obvious
like like navigation for instance
um
and um the the semantic modeling that
you mentioned i think it's also um
intuitively you can relate to how how
you can build a map from this and and
relate related there's also the
the the work from um
james whittington on the dolman icon bar
machine
that that goes in a similar direction
where he basically
builds a system that's
also
true
navigating a structure tries to
infer certain relationships and he also
applies the same model
on different kinds of
tasks so for example one task is
uh also navigation but like navigation
in the in a greek world like you can you
go north east west south and then you
expect to be in the same location again
but you can also he also applies it like
on family trees like um
john is the father of um
daniel and then daniel is brother of
blue then you could infer uh
who is a sister or daniel for example uh
and and
he also maps this in like navigating a
space
and and learning how how relationships
which which are then like actually
taking actions in the map it's like um
following the the the
the broader arrow it's like it's taking
an action uh in in in the physical map
let's say and then
you basically have to traverse through
the family tree only once but then you
basically know all the relationships and
you can start navigating and make these
kind of inferences so this is actually
pretty pretty cool work and there was
another i think there was another task
uh we also applied it on so
there are some tasks so it's really
obvious how to do it there are plenty of
others where it's not so obvious
but
yeah some somewhere uh adam and i
basically think yeah
this is kind of anything should be
mappable to the system and and this
could then be like a
universal way of of
how
how did humans come to
uh thinking in in these kind of abstract
levels well basically because they
evolved from a very good mapping and
navigation system
and that's kind of the the main idea so
if we can solve
how to build a map and then navigate it
uh first on the navigation level
and then on a more abstract level then
we might be on our way to to uh
kind of a general um system for for for
a reason
yes blue thank you
uh thanks that was super helpful so i
really um
yeah that that opened up a lot of doors
so in relationship to another project
that daniel and i are working on it
seems like um from the family tree then
it would be easy to map over like a
genetic space a genomic space or even
like a phylogenetic space from one
species to the next or even like mapping
over recipes um like when you're cooking
or even like different types of art
so just kind of anywhere where there's
the adjacent possible it seems like that
that's where you can construct these
kinds of maps that's really neat
oh god
yeah um i i i think the the main the
main thing is how
how do you transfer
the action concept to to the the space
that you're looking at like in a family
tree the action is like
moving from one person to the other and
the the action type basically defines
the relationship between two persons um
i think that's kind of the
difficult part always like which is the
action space that you need to traverse
the world and then the second thing is
like what are the what are the locations
in the world and once you can map these
two
then i think you're pretty pretty much
done right it's like
it's it's finding a way of moving from
one location to another via these
actions and if you have the actions or
relations between entities you can
basically draw
an inference on what is now the relation
between a and b
given this structure
[Music]
awesome a few
points so
tim thanks for beginning with this nice
description about how we could add in
this
conceptual or in cultural
layer
and about generalizing across different
environments
and that reminded me of the work on
pattern languages and it's kind of a
bottom-up discovery and then it was a
great point like yes there's the
algorithms that generate
a house scene
but there might be something that does
that at a pixel level makes sense like
putting a toothbrush under a cabinet but
then semantically or culturally a person
will look at that it's like but that
doesn't make sense
and so then that would be like let's
just say it explored a bunch of
different warehouses and the commonality
was like it was always
rectilinear
shelving
there's a genre of warehouse that's like
always that way and then whether it was
like three shelves by ten shelves or the
other way around
there would be like another space that
those graphs would map to so that was a
very
nice
um piece
and then um
chris feels and michael levin just a few
days ago
wrote this paper competency in
navigating arbitrary space intelligence
as an invariant for analyzing cognition
in diverse embodiments
so
perhaps something relevant for us to
explore going forward what do you think
blue
i think these guys write papers like
faster than i can read papers which is
amazing
i know it was um yeah april 24th so
three days ago i have not fully read it
but but a lot of the figures look very
interesting and
um
[Music]
so um
and then but i want to continue on this
last
point about the actions and maps because
that kind of mapping and multi-scale
mapping and transmuting and translating
across different types of maps
is
kind of the what the multi-level slam
is it's what a single level slam is but
then the composability of this
discussion is what enables like there to
be a slam where it goes from a geometric
space to a topological space and then
from that into like a cultural or
narrative space or something
so
how does action
relate to maps
and i thought about that family tree you
mentioned how there was one
representation where the actions were
like just like well you know if you're
in a room shaped like a bifurcating tree
then the actions would be you walking
around that room so that's one action
then there's the cognitive action
as that entity is building its
knowledge representation of the tree
and that that is related to its planning
and its
preferences or all of this that isn't it
inferring the tree but it's like
figuring out how it's going to infer the
tree
and then there's like there's other
actions though there's the action though
we won't talk about it of how families
arise
there's all kinds of actions and the
tree is just a representation of some
other
process
so how do we think about all these ways
that action relates to maps and what
kind of maps are actionable
what about ones that are about action
but not actionable or all this
other possibilities
yeah i
i'm not entirely sure whether i'm
all the way with you with your
with your last explanation so i i think
that the second bullet like the action
of updating the genetic model
i would not necessarily consider that an
action i think that the updating of the
genetic model just arises
from from experience and trying to
minimize your free energy
anyhow
the
the action from uh
from the uh
the other actions i think is
like
what is the action concept on different
levels
for example in it to be more concrete in
the
in in the genetic model
we had the low level action which is
basically
a velocity command for the robot like
move
forward
or or turn around with this kind of
velocity
but then the higher level action
concepts would be we called it the move
which is like traversing the space from
one location to another
which is kind of uh
in this case
uh of course graining of the low level
action but i think for every level in
your abstraction hierarchy
there will be
an action concept that moves from one
thing to another
and
what that concept has to be will be tied
to whatever level of abstraction you're
modeling at that stage i guess
but i don't see any other actions
besides that per se
thank you jim blue so i think about like
at different levels of actions if if you
for example think about foraging right
so you can have like camps of human
foragers and the task of each individual
forager is to go out and find food so
you go out you find food and you come
back and you go out and you find food
and you come back and then like if it
takes too long to find the food then
collectively as a unit the camp decides
to move right so so you pick up and you
make camp somewhere else so that's like
a an example of like every day the
individual unit does something um some
task and then the collective makes the
decision based on the on the input of
the individual foragers or like the time
it takes them to find food so that's
kind of a way that like i can think
about the nesting of um of action
yeah and so so
so so i think we're on the same page
on that account because you you will
have at some point a very high level
generative model that
that encodes in the state like um
do we have enough foods if not
we uh
we collect if we don't find foods we go
to another state so it could be like a
very high level abstract map with a few
states and notes and you could drop i
imagine you can draw out like
um
a graph with nodes where every node
is kind of a specific state and then
doing an action brings you from one note
to the other it could be a note like
not enough food enough foods um
move to another location and then you go
from
none not enough foods to foraging which
brings you either to
which either brings you in the same
state or brings you to the state i have
enough boot which is fine and if you
keep on uh
residing in the not in a food state then
you decide to move and you might
so you could kind of imagine an abstract
map where you have this kind of dynamics
and the actions make sense and then at
some
some point you will have the
the task or the action in this level
that says search for food which at some
level down the road will
will be
driving actions for start walking or
start navigating or search for places
where
that
that that are promising for finding food
so
lots of levels of of a conceptual
hierarchy you will have different kind
of actions that bring you from one note
to the other where the note might be
like a general state of the
community which is like the very top
level that you just described and then
you also have like nodes that are like
physical locations in your environment
and then you also have like very low
level nodes that might just describe
like uh your current pose in the world
basically and and the lowest level
action will just be the the torques that
you do or the the muscle the muscle
movement that you do with your legs and
your hands it will be the very low level
so i think
um
you can you can draw this concept all
the way up and down with the verb
with many layers of the hierarchy and at
each layer
going from one state to another
this is basically the action
at that layer but the meaning will be
yeah different depending on on which
level you are
and
the
the difficult part i think is how how
could you how can you have these
concepts emerge from from from bottom up
and i'm not sure that whether it's
possible but at least we are we're
trying to get us as as high up as we can
basically
very
interesting yes thank you blue
um
so it's super interesting and and
definitely um
it's why i link next to semantic space
because when you're trying to
like communicate with someone like the
purpose of communicating can be you know
have many faces but but in in
communication it's like reaching a
shared understanding
and then like okay we have enough
understanding of that topic like let's
move on to another topic in a
conversation and so um that's why that's
like
very easily um it's very easy for me to
see like how the semantic mapping and
the spatial mapping
um can can link together but i can't
think of like why
um i mean like why why would people like
well maybe in genetic or genomic maps um
that also makes sense right like to um
like like what would be the action like
to evolve i guess is the action in in
kind of a genomic map
space but like think i guess
um maybe novelty and that's kind of
where active inference comes in like why
would you traverse
a a map of recipes or a map of different
types of art um and i guess like the
idea is in um in exploration like and
trying like what happens if i combine
these ingredients in this other way or
add this other ingredient or like where
is the adjacent possible like that's
where i kind of think that the
exploration the room for exploration
comes in and so when you when you
traverse the map um sometimes the action
is just to
to see what's next or just to to explore
or reduce uncertainty about about your
possibilities or affordances
yeah so i think once you
once you've nailed down
[Music]
the different nesting of states and what
are the different actions you can take
that bring you from one state to another
on a certain level
then basically the the
what you will do
can emerge just from from minimizing
expected free energy right and that that
would be the the
the powerful ingredient or the powerful
um
tool that active entrance gives you is
that once you
you i i i would see
building a map and or like a more that
kind of grass structure where you
connect notes and and the transition
between notes or then the actions it's
kind of a way to
build the generative model
that is a bit more complex than well
actually it's not that more complex but
then than the traditional a and b
matrices
um
and and in that way
you can apply the same principles right
let me write this one very important
point down tim because you said maybe
you could just unpack this
in active inference
being able to
provide a structure of the model
provides us
a way to optimize it using variational
bayesian methods message passing
software toolkits like forney lab active
block for instance pi mdp matlab spm
and i think that's something that's
subtle but interesting and different
from a lot of other
models where the mere data structure
doesn't lend itself to like
an implementable algorithm
what do you think about that
yeah i think that's very true and i
think one of the
um
one of the important things also in in
the in the whole um
slam system here is that
we basically move from uh
more or less high dimensional continuous
observation
and action space i mean you could
you could do any uh continuous um
you you can command any any number of
velocity uh that is sensible to the
robot and the the amount of uh pixel
information that uh that you can get is
also uh
very big if not close to infinite so
we basically move from this high
dimensional continuous spaces to
something that is more like a discrete
set of nodes that you can traverse which
is much more like
an a and a b and a c matrix like like we
are used to in by mdp so
just by enforcing
the model to learn this more discrete
state space that's that we can manage
is already a a big step that's that
would allow for um connected or active
inference to to to be applied basically
because one of the the biggest issue is
always like okay
um
you could use active inference for
planning but if your your state space is
so large then yeah just
you cannot just iterate over all
potential
uh policies and and calculate the
expected free energy and and pick the
best one because your space just blows
up but if you
are able to at some level
discretize it's through a limited set of
states that are applicable to your
current context then maybe you can start
iterating through all the potential
relevant behaviors it's like
um going back to the
to the foraging example if
you just have to choose between moving
versus foraging the problem becomes much
more easy than when you have to decide
for an any possible muscle movement that
you can do the next few hours right so
i think moving to a more um discrete set
of
states
is is crucial to to to scale these
methods to to to realistic suffix
awesome
so returning to this maps of action
question
and that's a little bit in contrast with
like the maps of meaning and i think it
points again to active inference as
always having inference and action as
like two approaches to minimize free
energy two ways to think about the same
process
um
and
i want to return to this question about
like what the actions and the moves are
so i'm imagining
uh blue on the foraging trip
and there's what was the
um
the semantics of the slam presented in
this paper
was it was a
location
based approach whether in a geometric
space
or in a um in a topological in a
relational space but am i in the right
position like is a question about
location satisficing
and then it can also
be thought of as like that entity is
existing at a location in cognitive
parameter space because this question
about estimate about space is a
cognitive parameter it's one about the
territory it's a map of the territory
but these are cognitive parameters
that can include like
am i paying attention am i where i want
to be with respect to how i'm paying
attention about things
and so to actually explore that i wanted
to juxtapose
um
[Music]
two different generative models that
we've seen
and keeping in mind also that that
capacity of active inference where being
able to form these generative models it
also is
helping us get towards applying them
so on the right is the structure of the
model
from your paper
on the left is a three level model but
there's also a two level one that i can
pull up and it's from the sandvik smith
at all paper
on computational phenomenology
and mental action
and so the actions in this case
are happening at the level of what am i
perceiving what what is the action at
this sort of like motor level and
whereas in in your
multi-level slam
this
level
was about space still again from the
geometric smaller scale tactical scale
of space to the topological bigger scale
strategic level of space
but it's still about the territory
and in here
uh a somewhat analogous
multi-scale nesting of the
partially observable markov decision
process
is used to represent not a spatial
layer
or coarse graining
but actually in a tensional layer
so what do you think this what does this
make you think of or what does nesting
pomdps mean
and what could it mean
well in essence what it
what it basically does it puts
the higher level
it's like a prior on your lower level
right on the
on the the next so
in in in my figure like the
one
if you have um
if you have a belief over your state in
the red box
then basically this gives you a prior on
what you expect to
observe in in in a single blue box
and
in this case in my case it's indeed
very tight to the to the spatial domain
but in essence it can give you a prior
on on
on on any aspect of of the level below
right
and i think that's what they do uh on
the
on the in the left model then
where also if you have like an inference
on
um
[Music]
if you have a belief on the the orange
states in the left mole it basically
gives you a prior on what
what states you expect to observe
uh or to believe in the in the in the
blue one there here's going to be i
think this is figure 12 instead of
figure 5.
so this is the generalized deep model of
action and here the emissions
of the hidden state at the higher
internal mental level cognitive domain
the emission
mediated by the a
matrix just like it would be in a retina
but the emission of a is
the hidden state
at the lower level s uh one but also the
uncertainty parameters like the variance
estimates
on every
other
core um kernel parameter so yeah
so in the slam what other which of these
other generalized connections do you
think have
relevance for the robotic slam context
wait i think i think it makes a lot of
sense to also have like um um
something modulating your your uh your
precision parameters it's like it's like
it's like having a
certain
trust on your observations for certain
environments for example
you could you could
you couldn't for example if you go if
you go to your seller
you might know that the lighting
conditions will not be optimal and
you'll have different precision than
when you're in your kitchen for example
just thinking out loud so i i think it
makes sense to
to have this hierarchical structure on
any
on
on anything that that you have beliefs
over or that anything that can
have importance on on your on on making
better predictions basically so you can
have a less
you can you can have better predictions
if you have a good prior on
how precise you would expect your
observations to be here so that's why it
makes sense to
have a model evolved that that
takes this into account i guess
it just is very interesting like
if the nesting can represent
staying within the same domain
and of course graining of like okay you
know district states
continent like a sort of within the same
genre
but different course grainings
or it can seemingly
at least in the case of mental action
and
hyper prior optimization
modeling in general
like investigation and research in
general
those cases this is not a course
screening it's it's a something totally
different
so if the interface can mean two totally
different things couldn't it
couldn't there be a third
implication too
or
do these exhaust
the implications of nesting
can nesting only refer to like a like
kind nesting for example nested time
scales nested spatial scales
or
the cognitive action
of basically
removing something from the sensory
territorial
domain
and then like entering it once into the
cognitive domain
but then once it's been entered into
so-called hidden internal states which
are not even being proposed to actually
exist
in space or time
then you're kind of in
in like the matrix simulation slash
structure learning on cognitive models
and then it's not like that's going to
be nested
i don't know
but i i think it's just uh
in the end
it's it's just finding the um
finding the most simpler model that
explains it but not simpler right
and
you could imagine
a model that that operates on the lowest
level always
and
that indeed just has uh the case of a
robot has pixel inputs
and has
torque or velocity output
and
builds a model that can
predict
four hours in the future accurately
but then you also realize that this
should be a very very very complex model
it it it must always
it's almost the environment right
and
this is unknowledgeable and the only way
to kind of
do it then is to
to start adding structure to the model
and start um factorizing out different
variables and in essence nesting is
nothing else but factorizing out a
certain variable
so so
i think in the end it's just a matter of
finding
the model that
most accurately
predicts what's going to happen
with the least complexity and building a
hierarchical
nested model
is one way to to
to make this happen
the way that blue spoke about the
genetic
nesting in this sort of aristotelian
sense giving rise to in the genetic
sense and in the sort of cellular and
then how you framed it as the simplest
model but not any simpler which is often
at least in the bayesian area framed as
being like the aic or bic
pareto optimal model like some kind of a
trade-off of accuracy and complexity so
on
and
it's like there's a process of
structure learning
because we want to know okay
categorically should we be fitting a one
level two level model what kind of
structure within the three level nesting
which one of these edges are going to be
um making the machine learning model in
real life run a hundred times slower and
not even converge which one of these
edges are we going to be just totally um
in the dark without
bayesian model selection on structures
including cognitive structures
and those structures we're not picking
the final best this structure learning
is not picking the final best
parameterization
and this is kind of like how carl is
always speaking about developmental
robots
and how out of the factory or whatever
it's going to be in a learning
mode
so the structured learning is on
learning structures
and the learning structures are about
perception
including the actions that one is
observing themselves to be doing because
if we couldn't observe the consequences
um or at least even our own action
states in some way there'd be like a
total disconnect and our we could never
get our action policies
it would just be like the motor babbling
and the sort of uncoordinated movement
and i'm sure a lot of robotics and
evolutionary simulators
like that's why they have that wobbly
leg
phase
because i think a lot of those models
they don't know they're wobbling they're
just implementing like in this super
high dimensional space of motor policies
they're just
they're not getting the feedback so this
is it is like a nesting
um
cool very
interesting um
direction here and i think there's a lot
more to explore
about what kinds of nestings because
maybe it's actually that attentional
layer
that you described in your
opening thoughts
about the uh higher level of abstraction
that was taking in a graphical
a graph
i mean
you know maybe that is the layer that it
just comes on top right here and the
current the can
gets input into
some other
thing
let's uh look at some of the
formalisms and figures
or if blue or if anyone in the live chat
has any questions they can totally ask
i have a question on this or if there's
another
equation or formalism that
it's clearer to address this question
this
p
on the left side you can describe it in
your own words but it's a joint
distribution of multiple variables
how does one go from
knowing what
variables they want to include in the
joint distribution
like what arguments they want that
function to take
and then
a specific partitioning factorization
like is this the only factorization or
how do we make
this factorization based upon what we
kind of know what we want to model maybe
even very early
yeah so
so basically
going from the left hand side to the
right hand side
you can basically
um
one-on-one derive it from the figure
basically
so
if you look at the figure
you see that the
that pie
has no incoming errors
so
there will be no
conditioning on on pi
and then if you look at the action
uh um
notes
then you see that these all get an input
arrow from pi so then you know that
pi is actually influencing the action
that you do so this will be a
probability of uh action given by and so
that's basically how you could you can
write down
the equation just by looking at the
figure basically so typically how we
if we if we start off with a new with a
new type of model
we start off indeed with just listing
all the variables that we want to model
and then we start with drawing out a
potential diagram like we have on the
right
and
try to make sense out of that
and once we have that
the the equation just falls out
basically and it's always a matter of
thinking like
which variable has an influence on which
other ones
uh
for instance you can also mix make make
your own assumptions there like one the
assumptions that we
often make is like okay the hidden
states
should be kind of should be markup
markovian so
once we know the state at time t
we don't need any
information on the past anymore
uh to generate the current observation
for example so so these kind of
assumptions
um go also in and they will then decide
on
uh
on which things you need to
condition
because you could also
uh if if in general uh you have
uh the joint distribution you can also
just restrict yourself to basically base
rule to come up with the factorization
so that this could be then
p of pi times
p of
a given pi
times p of s given am pi times p of uh o
given s a pi so if you just use base
rule you can also come up with a
factorization that will be perfectly
valid but that might not
um
be easy to implement so you basically
search a bit for
what is uh
possible and you add some assumptions in
order to make it
work
intuitively
as well as practically
if that makes sense
thanks a lot so you mentioned the first
two terms here it would just be great to
hear for the green blue and the purple
term just how do you describe the way
that you look at the graph and then
translated it here
and then i'll have another question but
first up
yeah so the green blue and purple
yeah so for the green one you look at um
the initial
notes of the blue part so this it's like
your initial
uh
your initial state
uh at the start of sequence and you
cannot and this one it um
this one has now uh
oh yeah oh no this will be the yeah
sorry this will be the the ultimate
original
um stated
i don't think that um i don't think that
the
the equation on the left corresponds to
the uh to the figure because there's no
locations and moves in there
right okay yes this is a lower level
model that we're looking at yeah and yes
okay the initial condition is
conditionally independent of other edges
yeah
yeah and then and that so so the the
green and the blue is basically your
initial start state so you you have to
bootstrap somewhere so you have some
prior on your starting state and then
from then on the next states will all
depend on the actions you take so then
it's in the in the purple the first term
is basically saying okay my next state
will depend on my previous state and the
action i took
and then the
the second one in the purple is saying
okay the action that i take will depend
on my policy
and
the last term then just says okay my
current observation it only depends on
my current state because i assume that
all information of that time step is
basically
uh
um
it is represented in in in the in in
this state at that time
this is really
powerful and i think that the fact that
all future states
are part of a combinatoric
relationship with action it really shows
how deeply action is embedded within
active inference like there simply is
not
a consideration of future observations
or latent states
except for
conditioning action on policy
and conditioning states on action
so
policy is above actions that are
selected that are actually taken and
enacted
but all inference is conditioned on
action selection which is conditioned on
policy
and there aren't two separate models
like an expectation module and then like
an action selection state value mapping
um state policy mapping policy statement
all those kinds of constructs that are
meant to bridge the gap between
inference and action being two sides of
the same coin to minimize free energy
literally also for those machine
learning models
it's just really interesting how that is
all
concisely simplified and integrated in
active inference and so i want to ask a
question on this purple term
which is is anything known
about the computational complexity
of
changing h
with respect to
how you actually ran the models like
sort of in principle or how you actually
ran it like is it like if you go like
one two three four five time steps does
it go like time step squared is it like
time steps
triple squared or what is it
yeah so i think you have to distinguish
uh
two uh two differences here so
when when just
modeling the system
then h
doesn't really matter it's just it could
go to infinites
without without loss of generalization
so it's like your your agent gets bored
and then it's
it operates like this until the end of
its life and that could be hp so from
from just modeling the system
it doesn't really matter and just say
okay
this is the
the
the time
horizon i consider the system
and this is then how how i assume it's
it it acts basically
it's a different story if we look at an
actual implementation where
you suddenly have to um
yeah choose an age um yeah
if i implement this model how long do i
need
how long do i want this thing to be able
to predict because of course
if you
if you build a model that is predicting
and then you have to check uh whether
your prediction was correct and you use
the kind of models that we use that
basically want to back propagate all the
way back
to
to have a gradient update step
then of course the edge becomes
determined by practical
considerations like
how much memory does my machine have to
keep all these intermediate states and
memory and i can still back propagate
through
uh through this model um
so
so so then it
it's basically
an implementation implementation driven
choice on how how far in the future do
you want to model this thing uh
or can you model this thing because it
might also be that if you try to predict
too
far ahead
that
there's so much noise that it doesn't
even make sense to to try to predict it
so for the future so it can be um
it can be driven either by what makes
sense for this environment versus
how much
how much computes and memory do i have
to make this happen basically
awesome
blue do you wanna
yes go for it
so
i have a question over this figure and
then um also over the
it's formalism six i don't know if you
have that anywhere on the slides daniel
if you want to grab it
yep
okay so in uh
formalism six like the same observations
are there at both levels at the lower
level and the higher level and this
makes a lot of sense for something like
foraging right like the the lower level
the group is gonna the individual is
gonna go out move forward and then at
the higher level it's going to um the
group is going to move right so in a
hierarchical sense
um that makes sense and then
in figure two
um in the in the legend of the figure it
says that the higher level operates on a
coarser time scale
so where like the the lower level
decisions are made at you know 15 minute
time scales or one hour time skills the
higher level is like a day or something
some similar relationship um and that
also would make sense for something like
like foraging um this is kind of relates
back to the question of emergence and i
just wonder
if you can allow for
so like not all systems operate this way
and um you know here's the big big
question
right like like um
every uh like organ in my body does
something different right like so
and then like you know all my cells are
getting dehydrated and then suddenly
like i say i'm thirsty and i drink right
it's not like my cells cannot like move
to go like take a drink of water
so like in a hierarchical sense where
where the higher level is doing a
different action
than
the lower level have you thought at all
about how to try to navigate something
like this like we're at the higher level
the action is totally different well the
time scale might be coarser but but here
the variables change um and this is
something i think about a lot and so i'm
always collecting input and i just
wonder what you think time
yeah so
so basically the
i guess the the core question is
how
if you take a decision at the higher
level which is like a move in this case
how does it triple down to um
a lower level action
that might not even be related to
the move you want to make at the at the
higher level something like that right
so
basically how how this happens is that
if you if you look at a single level
um
so like a vanilla active inference
formulation
then at some point
you
you tie in the preferences from from a
prior it's like
these are my preferences so that's what
i want to obtain um in in
in this one level
and in the hierarchical model how how
how we do it is that basically the
the
the action
on the higher level so in this case
making a move to another location it
basically sets
uh
so if we if do you have a bigger version
of the
of the of the image maybe uh they know
so suppose that we go from um so we are
now at l big t
and we want to make a move to um l
big d plus one
so this basic so at some point this is
the decision we took we want to go to
the
to the other one
then basically we can use then the
um the a matrix or the the liquid model
that then says okay if i'm at l t plus
one then this is the kind of state and
pose that i expect
so this is then being fed back downwards
as like this is now the preference for
the lower level model to obtain
this kind of um state
and then at the low at the lower level
you again have your expected free energy
to work out the low level policy and
actions that actually bring you closer
to that kind of preference
but at the same time so at each
actual fine-grained tank step
you get low level observations that then
give you new beliefs over the state and
the pose you're in which might give you
more which might give you more
information on the location that you're
in and then either
at some point you will reach
the preferred location and then
okay great success
or it might be that something went
terribly wrong and you'll end up in a
different location
but then it basically
also goes up again and at the higher
level you'll then say okay i'm now not
at the location i wanted to be but
apparently some different one that i was
so then you start planning again
at that level to
to correct and
search for a new step to take that will
then ripple down as like a preference
for the lower level and that's how
everything kind of um continues on going
so
the
you have your your
the you use the likelihood model that
maps the states from higher level model
to i believe on
lower level states and these this
lightweight model becomes kind of your
preference for the lower level which
then has your inference process there to
do to infer the actions and that's how
you can kind of
decouple them
from semantic meaning as well
[Music]
this is awesome it reminds me of the
kind of
question that people often ask
where do you want to travel where would
you like to travel where would you
prefer to travel
it's often interpreted in a very
life scale
of analysis like i would really like to
go to this other area
so then that's like let's think about
that as the biggest level so where would
you like to travel i'd like to go to
california
how will you get there
i'll take a plane
where will you go to take a plane
i'll drive to the airport
how will you drive to the airport
i'll get in my car
how will you get in your car i'll leave
my room how will you leave your room
i'll get out of my chair like that's
very much the nesting between the top
level having more of like this
topological
where i want to be
which then is
imposed and propagated
as and sets the constraints and
opportunity for this lower level
like how i will get there because it's a
totally where would you like to go
somebody could think in their head i
want to go to california in my life
and then the answer to where you want to
travel would be like to the next room
but be like that wasn't really the scale
of the context of the question
but this like really shows how the the
multi-scale
nesting of location
lends itself to
heuristics and algorithms that help us
like chunk
complex navigation tasks like
navigating to somewhere in california in
the next few years
but you can't do the roll out for all of
the actions taken at the chair level
for that because it's going to be
too many
explosions of combo torques tim
yeah and just to to to add into in into
the storyline at some at some level in
in the hierarchy you you you are like
okay i want to go to my car
but then you could say okay but i need
my core can you say i don't know where
they are where are my car keys so then
suddenly from having this really goal
directed
nesting at some point you say okay i
need some more information
at this level to actually
reach my goal and so at that level it
might switch to more epistemic forging
which will then
um ripple down to the level below like
okay let's let's take a look in my
kitchen or at the kitchen table maybe
you're there and so that's how at every
level of the hierarchy you have this
exploitation exploration trade-off and
the outcome of that inference process
will then ripple down to the level below
like this is the preference for this
level to obtain and this is how
everything then um starts flowing
this is awesome blue
so i'm gonna now now ask another really
hard question so so this is really
awesome and it reminds me of um like how
the the higher level constrains the
actions at the individual level it
reminds me of um and i i know like you
were intending to take this out of
semantic space but it puts it back into
semantic space for me i was having a
conversation over the weekend in which
uh the at complexity weekend and one of
the participants brought up a kind of
political and controversial talk about
the topic and and i was you know they
said so so what do you think and i said
i think i shouldn't talk about that
and then they said
okay well so what do you want to talk
about
which is like kind of like a uh um
like an odd question to have in a
conversation but it constrains like when
you when you assign a topic or like here
i mean we're obviously assigning a topic
also um you know we're here to talk
about this paper and related things that
might come up but
in like a spontaneous conversation when
you assign a topic it very much
constrains the the the conversation to
um it limits the topic or at least
starts a seed
uh and i wonder like why do we have to
talk about anything like can't we just
sit or like can't we just like you know
talk about the first thing that comes to
mind or can't we just like be and be
quiet uh but for a lot of people that
that space is kind of awkward uh um and
where then does emergence fit into the
model which this is the hard question or
or can it fit into the model like when
um
you know what one
component of the lower level says well
maybe we'll move to the right and then
everybody says okay and they start to
pull to the right and then okay well
maybe we'll pull to the left like so so
does it is there room for emergence or
it's always constrained by the
assignment of the top level
yeah you spoke about the top level
propagating and rippling down so what's
the other
direction there
well i think
i think ultimately
you need um
you need some preferences at the highest
or at any of the levels right and if
there's
no such preference
then
indeed we end up in this situation like
yeah
what happens now and there's there is no
real constraint and anything can happen
but i think typically in life we're in
the at some level we'll always have a
preference and that
that defines our
our behavior
i i guess
i was i was actually talking to a
colleague on on similar things like as a
human we always have like we make plans
or
we have
there's always something on our mind to
do and we were like yeah but if you look
at the monkey in the zoo he just
he can just sit there
and do nothing
so what goes
what goes on in in in the animal's mind
is like okay all my preferences are met
i don't i'm not hungry i i have a safe
place
so i just do nothing
so yeah it's an interesting question
like
what what happens if we don't have
if we don't have any urgent preferences
that need to be met i don't know
well
in the zoo example that behavior of for
example low levels of activity might
also be associated with like learned
helplessness or trauma or like a freeze
reaction or the um
the
affordances are not presenting
themselves
in a in a certain way so then that
speaks like the ambiguity of cognition
with respect to behavior
and like the robot could be bumping into
the wall
for a lot of cognitive reasons it could
prefer to bump into the wall it could
prefer to do something else and so
there's like there's a many many-to-one
mapping
with
cognitive systems and behavior like
someone could be thinking
have different reasons or
preferences for why they emit
a given sentence so that's part of the
complexity but also like the opportunity
of the cognitive and then also the
classic lewis carroll quote um probably
also misquoted slash
alt quoted many other
places but it's like a great you know
folk
active
question
if you don't know where you want to go
then it doesn't matter which way you go
if you don't have high precision ish
on your preferences
at location
then
it's a wash it doesn't matter which
policy selection you're taking
because why would it the only way that
you could justify well well i like this
way okay because you have a preference
for simplicity or you want to head off
in this direction those are all valid
it's not to say that if you do know
where you want to go you're right or
you're doing the right thing or it's
going to be easy or possible it's just
like
if you don't have preference then it's
not possible
to make
any kind of decision worth evaluating
and that also speaks to the
the
integration of preference
in active inference as a means of
guiding epistemic and pragmatic value
rather than
reward learning reinforcement learning
which only centers on pragmatic value
and the implicit preference is more
reward would be better
and then there has to be all these ad
hoc ways of introducing epistemic and
balancing the paper clip maximizing into
these models
um blue and then tim
so great example daniel um and i think
back to uh
the monkey in the zoo and
if the preferences are the of the monkey
might just be constrained by the
zookeeper like the the monkey just does
whatever the zookeeper wants it to do
and then that made me really think about
um
parents and children in the united
states so is there always some kind of
downward causation right so so like if
you have a child um and in many families
and not only the in the united states
but it's different culturally right so
even the school system in europe is very
different than that in the united states
so the kids just kind of go to some
generic school the parents may or may
not have some preference for what they
want the child to be i want you to be a
doctor i want you to be a lawyer i want
you to take over the family business or
whatever and the child
grows in these constraints with this
predetermined idea so there's some kind
of top-down causation happening from
parents to children but in many
americans
and like we're just floundering over
here so so what drives then the
preferences of the
of the child when the when there's no
downward causation and and this is kind
of where exploration comes into play
right like so you might try this major
you might try that major or you might do
this or you might do that and you know
you have this this incredible amount of
freedom and so you really kind of don't
go anywhere or like maybe you take one
path in 25 different directions and then
just end up right where you started
so like you just start a whole bunch of
things and then don't really get down
make any progress on any one path in
contrast to europe where i think you
have to choose in eighth grade like stem
or not stem or something like this so so
it's it's interesting so so i think this
lack of downward causation so the
emergence may this is what i'm picking
up from our conversations the emergence
may come from
just an exploratory
an exploratory structure and like in
this exploration you just kind of find
some direction through exploration
thank you
maybe maybe two notes so so one thing is
if
if we don't have preferences then we
still have our information gain term
right so
this might drive you to
at least some
um
some form of exploration or some drive
to
kind of
at
at one point
infer as as good as you can where you
are
or on the or on the other hand
maybe uh some actions will
yield you more in more new information
to update your model like your the
information gain on your mobile
parameters so this might still drive
some exploratory
behavior
and then how how preferences come to be
shaped i guess one relevant uh
piece of related work is is done by uh
by north sagitt
on on uh her paper system where it's
actually all about
can you learn preferences from from
behavior where
the idea is kind of like
the the things you usually usually do
when you you're happy with
basically grow to be your preferences as
well and you're kind of attracted to to
revisit these states um
and
this also ties in like parenting like
just seeing your parents or having your
parents
um taking you to some states
just make it happen that these become
your preferred states also virtually the
the things that you just get to do
because that's what people around you
and you do
just become your preferences because you
you you see it being done and you're
doing it all the time so
by by doing it it becomes kind of your
your prior on things that happen and
that you have to do or that you are
expected to do and i i think
it's it's kind of related as well to
to the work of noor like how
maybe the things that that you you just
ought to be doing and that somebody uh
takes you to do become becomes kind of
your your preferences
great points so when you said that even
without preferences there's still info
gain
so that does hide a little preference
which is a preference to resolve
uncertainty but
if you remove that like preference or
assumption then it's kind of like okay
there's a million ways to make your
gaussian distribution worse
you can just inflate the variance and
your error will get infinitely high so
putting those types of inferences away
then there's the info gain approach
and then the the things that reminds me
of was the uh idea of novelty search
and so this is within the field of
evolutionary algorithms and evolutionary
computation where there's often this
very exacting
fitness
test
the top five percent fastest runners are
going to survive or they're going to be
evaluated on the task every single time
and then people realized and thought
about how well maybe it's not like super
harsh selection maybe they're sort of
oscillating selection pressures on the
task or maybe multiple tasks are being
selected and then sort of like the
um add absurnum but not to say
ineffective version of this argument is
forget the task and the performance and
the fitness on that task
and either entirely or partially use
novelty search
and simply sec select for novelty of
different kinds
and so it it does need to make its way
back to task performance like
homeostasis maintenance
but this is like an interesting thread
that was sort of like balancing out the
overly
pragmatic
value view and the second thing that it
reminded me of is the figure in
um
the active inference on discrete states
basis synthesis by decosta at all 2020
and so here um
[Music]
in the case of
no priors
on the left
bayesian surprise optimal beijing design
intrinsic motivation curiosity and the
infomax principle
and so it's like
interesting to see
how
under different special cases that are
shown here no priors
which might be no prior preference but
let's think about that
no ambiguity
like no no space between the observation
and the hidden state total observability
that's the mall
where we were speaking about the
robotics last time like where you can
just have perfect resolution of your
spatial location
then there's no ambiguity or risk a
deterministic action environment where
you know exactly how well each stock is
going to perform
then you can make expected value
decisions purely based around utility
and then no ambiguity or priors on the
right side here with maximum entropy
principle and jane's and max ends
so it's like this action perception loop
has so many degrees of freedom
that it's just wild
and the special cases
help us zoom in on like
the information gathering aspect of a
given level epistemic gain the utility
oriented components of a given level
that's the pragmatic
policy in the utilitarian component and
then
there's this balancing
of
the pragmatic and the epistemic and the
ability to flex and to adapt between
those which is why
some are excited about active inference
as speaking to this explore exploit
dialectic in a way that hasn't been
approached by like we'll learn a
parameter that switches between them
this is like a very different way
to
to integrate all those things by finding
an action perception loop that's a
generalization
of some of these cases
and it's really interesting that
um
this is a
discrete state space synthesis
so
all but implying that there hasn't been
a synthesis
on continuous and hybrid state spaces
so how do discrete and continuous
variables come into play in
just like this paper or robotics more
generally like how does that feels think
about discrete and continuous actions
yeah so in so in in this paper um
it's rather all contin it's uh i'm sorry
it's rather all discrete right so we use
discrete time steps
um
we
and
personally we didn't do a lot of
research on actually the continuous time
for formalism um
i know that for example pablo de nios
has done a lot of work and mathematics
in delft where they actually do the more
continuous time
torque control low level control of
robotic arms and so on
and there's uh it's an entirely
different formalism and i'm i'm
personally not too
i'm not an expert on on that kind of
systems but i i i i i guess that
similar
uh ideas um
are are there as well on the
information gain versus reference
resolving kind of
[Music]
planning
but yeah i i cannot really say a lot
about it
what is it like in this warehouse
like do people work in there or is it
just a test area or what is it on the
shelves
yeah it's just a test area so so
basically when we um
when we enter that particular building
this room was allocated as we we have a
data center in in the building so it's
the ground floor of our building
and this room is actually
um
allocated as as the
as a part of the data center but at the
moment we don't have uh
we don't have enough racks to to fill it
but it was like like to be future proof
and so
uh it was just an empty space
and then people started uh using it as
as storage space for all of the things
that are just
lying around and nobody really has like
a place for them to be so they they uh
they had some racks over there with all
kind of
random stuff that needs to be stored
somewhere like it's that you also have
like
a lot of old server cases from uh from
older machines over there that are just
sitting there in case we we need a spare
part or something so it's like it's like
generic storage space
and then we figured yeah if we have the
space anyway anyway we can start doing
experiments in this and so we have um an
area now where we have some robot
manipulators
uh and then at the same time we have
this more kind of warehouse setup that
kind of reflects how in in actual
industrial warehouses thing might things
might be and so you share the space with
um
with researchers working on wireless
localization that then
put some beacons on and see how the
wireless signal propagates with all
these metal shells around and these kind
of
things so it's just now a generic space
that we can use for
experimentation on navigation but also
localization
all
signal propagation through different
kinds of
material these kind of experiments all
happen happen there now
cool
the
part you mentioned about the the
electromagnetic radiation and how it
propagates it like makes me think about
how
you have this
current bot using only the visual light
like we kind of talked about that
previously it could have all kinds of
different sensors but it only has the
visual light
um and it doesn't use any kind of wi-fi
updating like what if every minute you
know it gets an update of its actual
location so that could be in the model
and then different kinds of
um
situations could be enacted simulated
and then enacted like what happens when
the lights go off
what if the wi-fi
goes down
and then
that
is where the generative model
being
on board
is
really
going to reveal
like the robustness of the approach
because if it does have this internal
spatial sense
the light's going off
may or going very dim which changes the
pixel values of every pixel and the
ratio of the colors and like everything
but maybe just the the
very light you know the the exit sign
that light alone is enough for the
camera to still do to relearn
and just have enough input from the
observation layer
so it's like very cool that you can
control the space like you have policy
over this space whereas in an operating
environment that you don't control it's
like you are subject to the generative
process
emitting actions to you
which might have regularity
or favorability but like you don't
control them and then that's what the
lab
is is like a space where
there are nest mates or robots or
learners but then the lab can also set
policy
with feedback from the bottom up but
also it is a place where the policy can
be controlled and that can help the
robot like learn and develop so that's
kind of cool
and it again it speaks to what carl is
saying about like the learning robots
like there is a time scale
at which the
community or the collaborators are in
feedback
with this
niche like without this paper or maybe
that yeah without this paper
there wouldn't be the discussion but
then without this being enacted that
wouldn't be the paper
so there's a lot of interesting dynamics
there
yeah maybe to to add-ons and errors that
you were describing on turning off the
lights and so on and using other sensor
modalities so we actually do have
experiments with um
with for example also modeling the so on
this on this robot in particular at the
front you see a planer lidar scanner so
it just scans
with a light ray and it measures the
distances um
and then the the red thing on there is
actually a radar so that's one chirps
and
at six
79 gigahertz chirps and then it listens
for the the reflecting signal and and
and that's also a way to kind of
estimate where are obstacles around you
and which distance are they and and
which velocity are they approaching are
going further from you
we actually
also create models on these kind of
modalities and and we could actually
show that it could kind of imagine uh
late lighter scans uh in inside the ale
or
how how radar would evolve if the robot
is moving
and
some other things that we did which was
uh these things are uh
especially ozone cattle who is uh the
first author of this paper as well did a
lot of work on this so so what one of
the the things he did was if we now put
like a gable gutter in one of these ales
then when the robot would drive over it
you would see
a whole different type of dynamics
because it would bump up and go down and
if you monitor
the
basin surprise so basically the detail
divergence between your
uh
between your dynamics model and then
your posterior you could see like a huge
spike in kind of surprise signal
on uh
on this kind of uh dynamics like this is
something weird that's happening and you
could kind of use this to to see is
everything going normal or is this
something weird going on
suddenly in in in my space
and we also did this where we had the
robot driving around but also people
passing by just walking by
and if that was in the center trains on
that model it would actually not be
surprised if it see if it sees uh people
passing by and if you would let it like
imagine
how would it be if if you drive forward
and sometimes you could see of course
very blurry because it's like a uh a
reconstruction we could you could see
kind of skinny
signatures passing by as if people was
as if a person was walking past a robot
like yeah this is a scenario that can
happen it just learned it
which was
pretty fun so maybe discovers the fun
fact
that is a fun fact
yeah
this is the total do uh
do robots dream of electric sheep like
that whole question it's like
if their generative model is generative
sure depends on what you mean by dream
if it's only a recognition model
probably not
that's very funny um
[Music]
let's take just one
last look since we talked a lot about
the factorization
of the one
level which was i think a great
discussion let's just look at the
factorization
of this multi-scale setting
and uh just
any other things that people want to ask
or any other thoughts you have but what
is happening with the factorization here
and similar to how you kind of like
um
gave a natural language representation
of the um
the factorization that we looked at
here
um
this is the single level just within the
blue level and so what is happening with
the multi-scale factorization
yeah so
if you here look at the at the bottom
you basically
um see again the
the the same kind of factorization as
you had before right so it's like okay
my current state depends on my previous
state and action and my action depends
on the policy
and my observation depends on my current
state and the only thing that is added
here is this um
uh the the
the term on uh p's which are the poses
so it's the the second term on the yeah
that uh
that one no
is pose
yeah exactly and so what we basically
what we did here is like since we
we are working on this uh
navigation setting and
we already had some inspiration from
existing slam approaches
we decide like yeah it actually makes a
lot of sense to treat
poses as kind of a first-class sentence
in in in the model and we
we really would like to have like
because you you kind of know how poses
evolve given the action right because
it's pretty simple uh
you can have a pretty simple uh
transition model that says okay if you
move forward then your pose will
increase in the direction that you're
heading basically so that's
a very basic way of of of entering your
pose and your poses is of course also
very relevant for knowing where you are
so that's why we decided to kind of
split off the uh
the abstract states and have an
additional
post state that was dedicated for um
for modeling uh where you are in in in
the space um like in in this uh in this
pose continuous attractor network
and then if we go to the level above
then there you have a similar structure
but now the action is the move and so we
have a prior on moves and then you move
from one location to the next given the
move that you're doing
and
then you have like the connection
between the upper level and the lower
level which is yeah what's now the
probability of
having a certain lower level state given
that i am in this location and what
would be my pose in uh of the robots if
i'm in this location basically
and
that then sums it up i guess
what is the purple term
and why is there the
big pie at the end of it
yeah so the
um the purple term basically is
your initial uh
your initial state for
a higher level so it's i think it's like
the
uh
if you look at the blue
box it's the
the gray
uh note
so it's like you you you observe
the initial um observation from the new
blue block facing that's your current
time step
cool
and then and then the the big pie is
then from then on you basically
uh go for a number of
like sub level lower level time steps
which is basically the
the counts that you make within the blue
box basically so we have like this
this big d and small t which basically
uh or are like to just denote
time step in within the the fine grained
level or time step within the
the orange level but
um
in
in actual timing
like the big d
uh
going from big d to big d plus one is
just like a number of time steps on the
actual
real discretized time let's say so
suppose if we say that our sensor
operates at 10 hertz like every 100
milliseconds you get a new observation
that's like the
the lowest granularity
timestamping
and then the the big d just is like okay
i i know i'm at uh
current time step and now it could be
one second later it could be two seconds
later could be five seconds later it's
just like
going from big t to big t plus one just
says there
some time has elapsed from going to this
discrete discrete thing that i call a
location to this next thing that i call
location but exactly how many
actual
seconds have passed yeah that's that's
up to the model basically because we
have this system that that looks at
how much surprise or how much um
information
that that's did i gain from
uh
from moving
and this basically determines when you
shift from one location to another so
the the concept of location is based on
this threshold on when we add a new node
to the map so we we added this
big d
uh notation just to
introduce kind of a
time step on the higher level but this
is totally abstracted from the actual
timing
which you do have for the lower level so
the lower level there the small t is
actually um the rate at which your
observations come in basically so this
could this could be fixed to like 100
milliseconds every 100 million seconds
you shift time step but when the big d
shifts it all depends on when you infer
to be
in a new location basically
if that makes sense and you mentioned
that there was a parameter you kind of
just empirically determined when it made
sense to add the new node um yeah but
then the the frequency of the discrete
time steps at the bottom was 100 hertz
like so 100 um or 10 hertz 100
milliseconds and that was just the
sampling rate of all of these
features
um
wow there's so much happening with
nesting
there's the movement from the geometric
to the topological
there's the movement from something that
is
at a smaller finer scale to something
that is enclosing it
really enclosing it
or conceptually
enclosing it in this kind of way that we
were talking about the cognitive domain
earlier there's this movement from the
kronos
to the kairos
from the actual
sensor
defined speed that things are happening
in the world to like the timeliness
of when it's
time to think that you're in a different
location and then in the biological case
it it was woven so clearly to this
multi-scale navigational capacity of the
of the he
system
because like if you said i'm in a
different place
in my room that might be
a foot but if it to be in a different
place on the train might be the next
train spot and so the way that language
is
vague yet
does allow us to really drill
into what model
what was valuable about that for you
what were you curious about in that
moment
like these kinds of ways that we
interrogate ourselves and that we can
also engage in conversation so yeah blue
why don't we
sit silently
maybe for
you know performance art stream number
one it could happen but also there's
uncertainty to resolve and uh message
passing to be done otherwise it's
implausible that we're gonna coordinate
in
our like
actions or in our
thoughts
um
if you have any other like ideas or
thoughts or questions or places you want
to jump to
we can totally do so otherwise this is a
great
thought too
what are the next steps you've mentioned
several things but just
what would be like a next outcome or
deliverable or thing that you're hoping
to see in the niche and maybe even enact
yourself
yeah some of the
things that i was discussing today with
one of our one of the students just
today actually is to
um
to basically
uh work on
can you
because one of the biggest limitations
now is that
in order to navigate you're basically
limited to
what it has seen before right so we
still need the um
we still need to hand control the robots
through the lab to build a map and then
only when it had has visited
the whole space it can start
it can even just then start navigating
it basically
so one direction is can we kind of
have the robot itself
um navigate
and one idea there is to
again
linking to our story about preferences
at different hierarchical levels
maybe we could have like a
preference on the lower level that just
says okay i don't want to bump into
things
and
um
if you don't have a map
the only thing you you want is
on the one hand be curious and and try
to update your model as good as you can
but also not bump into things and then
you have like this robot that just
starts driving around and at the same
time building a map and then
[Music]
at least you you
can can just put it anywhere it will
start mapping and at some point you can
you say okay the robot now you know go
to uh
now search for this particular object
and then you give it the goal and it
starts exploring
um
maybe it can imagine oh this is maybe
the location where i lost saw something
very similar so this is probably the
location i want to go to um and and then
you can have it like more gold directed
behavior so this is one thing uh we were
thinking about and then another
limitation is also that like the edges
between the notes are also only the
edges that you actually
um traversed once
so for example one
one stupid thing is that it it does not
know that if um
if it went from one location to the
other it can actually turn around 360
degrees and go back and it will be at
the same location because in this visual
space that might be a totally different
thing and if if you never
thought it
or actually control that you turn around
360 degrees it will never make the link
okay i can actually do this so one of
the
things that we were exploring so that
can we use our lower level genitive
model to kind of
imagine
potential links between notes and then
kind of add these
links to the map as if you kind of
um
visited those before or maybe add some
weight to these links so you know yeah
this this might be a link and this is
the likelihood of this link but at least
you can take them these links into
account when planning is okay i'm
feeling adventurous so maybe it's time
to explore this link or um
for this particular goal if this link
exists i never tried it but if
it exists it will it will be a huge
shortcut to reach this goal so i'm
willing to take this gamble
in this situation and to have like these
kind of uh behaviors by by just kind of
imagining
which kind of locations can i visit that
maybe i never tried this before but
given the the things i've learned from
this environment this might be the case
so i'll just try it uh so maybe this
kind of um
these two points are basically are the
next things
on our lists to uh to start exploring
nice it is like
knowing
other streets you could take
what if the road i always take is
blocked
and then
there are so it's just cool and what
arises after your
after you're implementing it and and in
the chat stephen has been making some
comments about the door and we discussed
like being in the hallway and then
there's the pixel contrast and then like
if there were a higher level concept of
door
probability of a door at that location
so that that pixel change abruptly could
be associated with a door
and then
then there's this
location of door
not just the pixel level mapping but
then there's like what does the door
bridge to
and
what if it explores a closed room and
now the door opens
and then it can say well now i'm curious
about what's out
there or like what is that node a
bottleneck and that's like the door as
markov blanket you know what's what
happens when you train it up on the
warehouse including with curiosity and
then you open the door what's gonna
happen
but these are awesome directions so
thank you for
sharing it blue do you have any final
comments or questions
thanks this was super interesting to
think about and explore and try to map
on to my map of my cognition in my mind
yeah agreed it was really cool to see
the the analytical formal and the
biological and the robotic
coming together
and so
much appreciated tim for joining us and
to adam for joining previously and all
the other authors so
hope to see you around
yeah it was also for my site was a a
nice discussion opened up a lot of new
perspectives also for me and new ideas
so uh thank you for that
thank you tim see you later thank you
blue
[Music]
you